甘尼克斯已经证明了自己
Gannicus has proven himself,
赐予他的奖赏是自由
let him be rewarded with freedom.
你赢得了鲁迪斯
You have earned the rudis.
证明你不再是个奴隶了
proof you no longer stand a slave.
你的爱妻背叛了你
Your wife betrayed you.
最后一次上床
One last fuck.
我们罗马战士要拼到最后一滴血…
And we will fight till the last drop of Roman blood
我不是罗马人
I'm not a Roman.
妮维雅死了
Naevia is dead.
你他妈的混蛋
Fucking shit!
我要杀了你
I'll fucking kill you.
你疯了吗
Have you lost mind?
妮维雅还活着
Naevia lives.
我才不要为这事儿送命
I will not fucking die for this.
不要让他们今晚就倒在了这里
Have these men not fall here tonight,
让他们去角斗场 当着整个卡普亚战死
but in the arena before all of Capua!
先取得你父亲的同意解除婚约
Gain your father's approval to dissolve your marriage,
再带着你湿漉漉的身子来找我
and find me as wet with desire as you now stand.
《斯巴达克斯：复仇》
《自由》
杀 杀 杀
Kill! Kill! Kill!
精彩的对决
A fine showing.
将永远为狂热的民众所铭记
To be forever remembered by adoring crowd.
正如赐予他们如此盛宴的
As will the name Varinius,
你瓦里留斯的名字
who bestows such generous gifts.
的确
Indeed.
他永远不会被忘记
He shall never be forgotten.
有的人就未必了
Same cannot be said of all men.
真希望有更多像你一样的人
Would there've more stood your equal.
可惜世上唯一的瓦里留斯
A pity there is but one of him,
很快就要受召回罗马了
so soon recalled to Rome.
您此行短暂 却使我们获益良多
A brief yet profitable stay.
您慷慨举办的角斗比赛
Your games have given the city
对于这座城市来说真是雪中送炭
much needed distraction in these dark times.
行刑开始了
The executions begin.
为我们卡普亚此行画上完美的句号
A glorious finale to our stay at Capua.
要是斯巴达克斯也在就好了
If only Spartacus were among the condemned.
他早晚逃不了一死 蒙卡图
The man shall be put to grass soon enough, Mercato.
我的手下正一步步逼近他
My men move towards this very purpose.
在此之前 我们就拿鲜血盛宴
Until such a time let us send message,
震慑那些叛贼吧
punctuated in blood.
汉尼拔来了
Hannibal stands at our gates!
这是罗马人用来吓唬小孩的说法
A phrase used to invoke fear among the children of Rome.
迦太基野兽的幽灵
A specter of the Carthaginian animal
多年以前曾经笼罩着这座城市
who besieged this city with terror and death many years past.
但正如共和国所有敌人的命运一样
Yet as is the fate of all enemies of the Republic,
汉尼拔最终命丧罗马人剑下
Hannibal passed from this life at the end of a Roman sword!
叛贼斯巴达克斯终有一天也是同样的下场
A fate that will one day be shared by the rebel Spartacus!
不正是你的远房亲戚
Was it not your distant relative,
阿庇乌斯•克罗迪斯•帕尔契尔
Appius Claudius Pulcher,
在卡普亚的首次战斗中
who failed to defeat Hannibal
败在了汉尼拔手下吗
in the first battle of Capua?
是的
It was.
尽管诸神尚未赐予我们如此愉悦的时刻
The gods have yet to bless us with such glorious sight.
却让我们看到了这一天来临前的曙光
Yet they grace us with portent upon horizon!
斯巴达克斯最为倚仗的三条走狗
Three of Spartacus' most trusted men,
他们的死可以警告所有胆敢挑战罗马的人
their deaths to serve as warning to all who would challenge Rome!
杀了这帮畜生
Kill those bastards!
准备受死吧 你们这帮混蛋
Get ready to die! You fuckers!
今日胜出成为骁将的勇士
Their blood to be shed at the gladium
将在竞技场上
by the warriors whose victories
亲手结束他们的性命
this day have earned them position in the primus!
谁能领导罗马的行刑者
Yet who shall lead the forces of Rome?
谁配得上如此传奇的一战
Who deserves such storied battle?
只有一个人
There stands but one!
本城唯一一位
The only gladiator from this fair city
在竞技场赢得自由的角斗士
to ever earn his freedom upon the sands!
真正的竞技场之神
A true God of the Arena!
有请
I give you...
甘尼克斯
Gannicus!
甘尼克斯 甘尼克斯
Gannicus! Gannicus! Gannicus!
杀了他们 甘尼克斯
Kill them, Gannicus!
杀了他们
Kill them all!
他为什么要这么做
Why would he do this?
因为他是一个毫无荣誉的人
Because he's a man without honor.
我们终于在竞技场上见面了
We at last face each other upon the sands.
正如梅莉塔所害怕的
As Melitta always feared.
谣言是真的吗
Is it true?
她去世的前一晚
Did you lay with her,
你跟她上床了
the night she left this world?
奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus
开战
Begin.
(一天前)
我们不应该兵分两路
We should not have torn our forces.
如果当初跟你们一起进了矿区
If we had been with you at the mines...
更多的人会死在矿坑里
Even more would lay dead within its tunnels.
大家都有错
Mistakes were made on both sides.
如果总是耿耿于怀
Let us place them behind us,
早晚会重蹈覆辙
or risk finding them repeated.
我们有发现了
We have found something...
诸神总算给了我们一点好处
Finally, the gods show fucking favour.
先看看是多大的好处吧
Let us see to what extent...
把大家带过来
Bring the others.
四处搜寻
Search for weapons.
说不定有留下的武器
Something may have been left behind.
终于有遮风挡雨的地方了
A roof over our heads.
勉强算是吧
Ah, mostly.
我们得养精蓄锐 计划一下未来
We shall take rest, consider future.
在老子的神庙里
There holds none for you
你们可没有什么未来
in my fucking temple.
看来诸神终于要送老子上西天了
So the gods finally fuck me to the afterlife.
不如一起去吧
Care to join me?
我们只是找个栖身之地
We seek only shelter.
别无所求
Nothing more.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus
你是斯巴达克斯
You are Spartacus?
正是
I am.
那是我有眼无珠了
Then I mistake fucking for blessing!
这座神庙好多年没人光顾了
This temple has remained absent worship for many years.
这儿虽说没啥好东西让人享受
It does not offer much in the way of comforts,
不过有我的自然有你们的
but I would share what I have.
感谢
Gratitude.
罗马人说的话 送来的酒 你敢相信
You would trust wine and words from a Roman shit?
那你又是什么东西
And what are you?
这么没教养 是高卢人吧
A Gaul, by your lack of manners?
我才不是高卢人
I am no fucking Gaul.
我叫艾力冈 来自莱茵河东岸
I am Agron, from the lands east of the Rhine.
我叫卢修斯 是罗马西莲氏族的
And I am Lucius, a Roman of the Caelian clan.
真是他妈的幸会了
A pleasure to make fucking acquaintance.
你为什么来这儿 卢修斯
Why are you here, Lucius?
我以前的住处可气派了
I did have more esteemed lodgings once.
一座宅子
A villa.
有土地 有马
Land, horses.
还有家庭
A family.
全让苏拉昧着良心夺走了
Struck from this world by Sulla's black heart.
苏拉
Sulla?
他也是罗马人
He too was a Roman.
却反过来杀害自己人
Yet marched upon his own people.
镇压胆敢反抗他的人
Punishing any who dared to defy him.
你听到我的名字时 似乎眼睛一亮
Your eyes seemed to brighten, when you heard my name.
罗马人不该这样
Unexpected from a Roman.
他们也屠杀了
The ones I held to heart
我的至亲们
were slaughtered by the same.
他们早已不是我的族人了
They stand no kin to me now.
然而
And yet
谁让他们受苦受难
the man who would make them suffer,
我就和谁称兄道弟
I would gladly call brother.
这些话怎么不早说 现在连酒也没了
You could not have made speech before swilling the last of the wine?
早知道你们光顾神庙
Had I known you were for this temple,
我就攒满一屋子好酒
I'd have stocked it to the fucking rafters.
我听说很多人死在卢卡尼亚矿区了
I thought the lot of you fallen in the mines of Lucania.
你从哪儿听说的
Where have you heard such tale?
在那不勒斯的街道上
In the streets of Neapolis,
那里消息很多
frequented for trading.
听说你们失败 整座城市闹得沸沸扬扬
The city is afire with news of your defeat.
幸存者即将在瓦里留斯的比赛中处决
The only survivors to be executed at Varinius' fucking games.
幸存者
Survivors?
知道名字吗
Give names.
我只知道有三个人会血洒沙场
I know only that three stand for the sands ...
其中一个被称为战无不胜的高卢人
and one by word marked as the undefeated Gaul.
克雷斯
Crixus?
他还活着
He yet lives?
只是再多活一天罢了
Only to see sun break dawn once more.
比赛就快要结束了
The games come to an end when it sets.
他们也即将没命
As do the lives of your men.
斯巴达克斯逃过一死
Spartacus yet evades death.
我们却要死翘翘了
While we fucking embrace it.
我可以等到妮维雅了
As I will embrace Naevia.
我在另一个世界等她重回我的怀抱
When she is returned to my arms in the afterlife.
梅莉塔也在那里等你
Where Melitta awaits you.
我渴望已久了
I long for reunion.
还有话要问她呢
And the answers it will bring.
民众是何等疯狂啊
How you will stir the crowd!
到处都是甘尼克斯如何英勇的传说
Tales of the prowess of Gannicus yet fill the air,
堪与赫拉克勒斯(大力神)媲美
rivaling those of Hercules himself!
他得到的奖励是不朽的生命
His labors were rewarded with immortality.
你多幸运啊 我只要银子就行了
Fortunate for you I seek more earthly payment.
事成之后一定给你
To be provided upon completion of your services.
我缺钱花
I find myself light of coin.
给我一点儿吧 只当是定金
A few dropped in hand would anchor purpose.
当然
Of course.
我可不希望等到约定的时间你就消失了
I would not wish to see wind carry you aloft short of the appointed hour.
你就放心吧
I shall see it done.
到时候肯定很壮观
It will be glorious spectacle!
来
Come!
我带你去见行政官和民政官瓦里留斯
I would present you to the Magistrate and Praetor Varinius himself.
让他们和那些大呼大叫的人一道
Let them gaze upon the legend in the arena,
在竞技场目睹传奇吧
with the rest of the howling mob.
我要去喝酒了 还要找女人玩玩
I am for wine, and the embrace of questionable women.
他怎么死的
How did he fall?
我们追踪的时候碰见了斯巴达克斯他们
We came upon Spartacus and his men while giving chase.
就是那个混蛋杀了他
The villain himself delivered grievous injury.
而你还站在我面前
And yet you stand before me,
能说能走
drawing breath.
我救了你的护民官
I came to your tribune's aid,
给他的伤口止血 保住他的性命
pulling him away to staunch life flowing from wound.
多么高尚啊
Noble effort.
- 可屁用没有 - 民政官
- Bearing no fruit. - Praetor
告诉阿比努斯元老
Send word to Senator Albinius.
斯巴达克斯不能跟那些奴隶一起
Spartacus will not be among the slaves
在明天的比赛中处决了
executed at tomorrows games.
叙利亚人呢
And the Syrian?
他可以在战场上证明自己的价值
Oh, he will yet have chance to afford himself in battle.
在竞技场上
In the arena,
跟那些没用的奴隶一并处决
to be executed with the other worthless slaves.
不要 民政官 求你了
No! Praetor, I beg of you!
民政官
Praetor!
又让人失望了
Yet another disappointment.
可怜的盖尤斯再次让斯巴达克斯逃了
Spartacus evades poor Gaius once again.
色雷斯人缺席 你的比赛恐怕会失色不少
I fear your games will suffer from the Thracian's absence.
蒙卡图向我保证过 场面一定很精彩
Good Mercato assures me grand spectacle.
我不会让你丈夫的失败搅了大家的兴致
I would not have your husband's failure dampen spirits.
我也不会让他保住这个身份
As I would not have him remain so titled.
我们就是来讨论这件事的
The very purpose of our gathering.
听说你有意娶我的爱女 我很高兴
News of your desires towards loving daughter lifts heart.
但我们不能操之过急
Yet we must proceed with caution.
婚约解除之前
I would not have Gaius aware of our plans
我们的计划不能让盖尤斯知道
until presented with dissolution.
那就容我们先告辞
Let us take leave,
好好讨论怎样行动
and further discuss how to proceed.
我盼着早日摆脱束缚
I long for constraints to be shed,
跟你一起回罗马
and our fortunes returned to Rome.
我也盼着你早日到我身边
As I long for you by my side,
成为我的妻子
holding position of wife.
按计划拿掉累赘
Remove encumbrance as discussed,
确保办成这件事
and we will see this to proper end.
累赘
Encumbrance?
我要解除和他的血脉联系
I am to untether myself from unfortunate lineage.
你要打掉亲骨肉
You would see your child never born?
这是必要的牺牲
A necessary thing.
确保有正统的继承人
To ensure a more worthy heir.
我欠你一份情
I am in your debt.
斯巴达克斯说了你为纳西尔做的事
Spartacus told me what you have done for Nasir.
如果不是你…
If it were not for you...
他是为了我才差点丢掉性命
It's because of me that he lays near death.
他们不应该到矿上去
They never should have come to the mines.
我也尽力阻止过他们
I did what I could to stop them.
可你做的还不够
Would that you had done more.
妮维雅…
Naevia...
我活着的唯一希望就是再见他一面
The hope of seeing Crixus again was all that kept me alive.
我每天祈求诸神让他回到我的怀抱
Each day I begged the gods to see him to my arms.
难道就求到了这个结果
And this is how they fucking answer?
只是匆匆一眼
By allowing his touch,
就永远地从我身边夺走
only to be ripped from it forever?
没人能动摇他救你的决心
He would not be swayed from attempt.
他们都是一样
None of them would.
我真希望露迪雅当初杀了我
I wish Lucretia had taken my life.
克雷斯就不会为了我这样的废物
Then Crixus would not have to sacrificed his
而牺牲自己
for something soiled and ruined.
斯巴达克斯有事找你
Spartacus calls for you.
纳西尔
Nasir?
他还在抗争
He yet fights.
我们都是
As do we all.
罗马人可就不这么想了
The Romans would have it believed otherwise.
卢修斯说有人传言
Lucius tells of spreading word,
我们全军覆没了
that we are all but defeated.
那就放马过来
Let them come.
让他们看个清楚
And find assumption false.
我不想再等下去了
I would not wait for such a day.
不想再看到兄弟们死在竞技场上
Nor see our brothers fall in the arena.
你要攻打竞技场
You would lay attack on the arena?
我们势单力薄
Our numbers are low.
能上阵的就更少了
More so of men able with sword.
葛雷博和他的军队自然也清楚
A thing known by Glaber and his soldiers.
所以绝对想不到我们会突袭
They would never think us to make attempt.
真他妈亏你想得出来
For good fucking reason.
谁还能比曾经在那里面
Who is more familiar with the arena,
拼命厮杀的人更了解竞技场
than men who have fought upon its sands?
你想怎么干
What are your thoughts?
近日的行刑其实是杀鸡儆猴
These executions serve as message.
警告世人罗马会摧毁任何企图反抗的势力
That Rome will smother any flame that burns against it's rule.
我也要回敬他们
I would send message of our own.
把所有奴隶心底的怒火点燃
One that will ignite the hearts of all yet enslaved.
确实很难下手
It is a heavy burden.
亲手扼杀你肚子里的骨血
Stilling life that grows inside you.
我先前想得太轻松了
I had thought deed of lighter concern.
也不知道为何下不了手
I do not know why I pause.
女人生性就是要保护孩子
A woman will always be moved to protect her child.
可我别无选择
Yet it must be done.
可能晚点动手才是明智之举
Perhaps it wise to delay the act.
你缺席竞技场的事 肯定会引起注意
Your absence at the games will draw notice.
缺席
My absence?
我曾经让巴蒂塔斯家的很多奴隶
I have forced silphium on many slaves,
你会感到虚弱
You will sicken.
还会失血
And bleed.
持续好多天
For many days.
如果你父亲非要你这样做
I will attest such to your father.
我可以帮你在他面前说明
If he so presses for reason of staying hand.
你的建议很好
You prove wise counsel.
我愿意一直帮你参谋
A service I would continue to provide.
你想跟我去罗马
Do you wish to accompany me to Rome?
我只想追随在你左右
I wish only to be at your side.
我们之间有很多难以释怀的过去
There is yet much of the past between us.
那就看看有没有未来吧
Let us see if there is a future.
快点
Be quick.
终于还是来了
At last she comes.
我有别的事情要处理
Other matters have drawn my attention.
那现在也该解决我的事情了吧
I would see it towards current fucking plight.
你觉得我会眼睁睁看着你送死吗
Do you think that I would allow you to perish upon the sands?
你为我做了那么多
After all you have done for me?
我会跟葛雷博谈谈…
I will break words with Glaber
没抓住斯巴达克斯的责任 他怪到我头上了
He places blame for Spartacus evading capture.
他不会听你的
He will not listen to you.
但他会倾听诸神的意愿
Yet he will heed the will of the gods,
正如他先前所做的一样
as he has so graciously in the past.
我会告诉他的
I shall whisper of them.
你如何从黑暗森林回到我们身边助一臂之力
Of how you were returned to us from dark woods for a purpose.
诸神对于你有何安排
Of how the gods yet have use for you.
和我一样
As do I.
你想让我做什么
What would you have of me now?
伊莉西娅的珠宝盒里有个红色的小药瓶
There's a red vial secreted among Ilithyia's jewelry.
我想让你把里面的东西换成苦草和水
I would see its contents replaced with water and bitter herb.
我曾经在这宅子里见过红色的药瓶
I've seen such red vials within this house before.
也见识过它的效果
And witnessed their effect.
如果药瓶没有起作用
And when none are presented,
那就说明上天注定要这孩子降生
it will be taken as a sign that her child must be born.
这事你自己来不是更轻而易举
A task easier seen by your own hand.
你和她很亲近 在宅子里行动更自由
You are close to her, and move freely through the villa.
我一旦被发现 风险太大
The risk of discovery is too great.
不能让伊莉西娅有理由怀疑我
Ilithyia must be given no reason to doubt me.
否则我们都完了
Or all will fall to ruin.
你让我怎么办得到
And how am I to do such a thing?
即便我自由了 我也不是幽灵
Even free of bondage I am no spirit,
可以畅通无阻地进门
able to pass through fucking gate.
我以前不是这宅子的主人吗
Was I not the domina of this house?
进门不是问题
Gates part in remembrance...
要是我被发现了呢
And if I am discovered?
别被发现
Do not be.
为了获得自由
I will see myself freed of bondage.
我什么都干
At any cost.
这种事情可能做到吗
Is such a thing possible?
我能做到
I would see it so.
大不了跟克雷斯死在竞技场
Or fall with Crixus in the arena.
如果诸神保佑的话
If the gods yet care,
也许你们能平安归来
may they speed your return.
我们要去哪儿
Where do we go?
纳西尔
Nasir.
把剑给我
Give me a sword.
我和你们一起走
I will join you.
我要你再休息一段时间
I would have you rest yet a while longer.
这次你留下
This time you stay.
我去杀敌
And I go.
我们得行动了
We must move.
这孩子死里逃生
The boy cheats death.
也许是好兆头
Perhaps it is a sign.
我们不能依靠兆头
We can not rely on omen.
我们的力量来自于正义以及实现它的决心
We must take strength in just cause, and bring it to bear.
你们都听到了关于我们行动的闲言碎语
You have all heard whispers of what we attempt.
现在由我来给大家确定的消息
I would overtake soft voice with bold words.
我们要去卡普亚的竞技场
We are for the arena in Capua.
那如果你们回不来呢
And if you do not return?
卢修斯•凯利乌斯知道该去哪儿
Lucius Caelius knows these lands.
如果我们去的时间太久
If we are too long from you,
那我请求他给你们指一条明路
I would ask that he show you safe path.
远远地离开葛雷博及其爪牙
Far from the reach of Glaber and his soldiers.
我们都饱尝了痛苦
We have suffered wound and loss.
与家人分离
We have been divided.
但我们是自由的
Yet we are free.
自由是无价的
A thing beyond price.
我要让身陷囹圄的兄弟再次获得自由
A thing I would see condemned brothers embrace once again.
同时这一举动
And in the doing of it,
也是向所有仍卑躬屈膝的奴隶宣告
spread word to every slave yet beneath heel
所谓强大的共和国 也是能击垮的血肉之躯
that even the mighty Republic bleeds when struck.
你真是威猛无比
You fuck like a god...
我也想来一杯
I would share a cup...
恢复一下气力
to regain sense...
我以前没见过你 对吧
I have not seen you here before, have I?
我已经好多年没回卡普亚了
I've been many years from Capua.
那什么风把你吹回来了
What brings return?
为了比赛才回来
I come for the games.
真希望我也能看
I wish I could see them.
我宁愿换下位子
I will trade place.
你站在沙场上
You stand upon the sands
我就喝个痛快 操到死为止
and I will drink and fuck until the gods take me.
沙场
The sands?
你是甘尼克斯
You are Gannicus!
那个赢得自由身的角斗士
The gladiator who gained his freedom!
灰暗无望的自由
Shadow of the same.
我还没听说过有别人赢得鲁迪斯呢
I've never heard of another who's won the rudis.
我能摸摸吗
May I touch it?
这些记号
These markings...
是你的胜利记录吗
They tell of your victories?
是沙场的荣耀 已经遗忘太久了
They tell of glories, long forgotten.
既然看到了不舒服 为什么还带着
Why do you carry it, if it troubles mind?
我必须随时带在身边
It must always remain at my side,
即便是在竞技场
even in the arena.
以此证明我不再是奴隶
Proof that I am no longer a slave.
也提醒我还是奴隶时所作出的抉择
Reminder of choices made while I was yet one.
梅莉塔
Melitta!
呼吸
Breathe!
闲话到此为止
Let us put talk behind us.
我要睡觉了
I would fall to bed.
美酒 还有你的美腿
Wine and the memory of your thighs
是我迎接明天的动力
to brace against coming day.
这样也好
It is a blessing.
再也不用回到这该死的宅子了
To be forever removed from this fucking house.
真希望看它化为齑粉
May it crumble in our wake.
把他们带到竞技场去
See them delivered to the arena,
准备行刑
prepared for execution.
遵命
Praetor.
民政官大人
Praetor!
抱歉 能和您说句话吗
Apologies, I would have word.
我暂且饶你一条命
You draw breath only because Lucretia
是因为露迪雅说诸神预言你还有价值
cautions the gods yet foretell of your worth.
再惹我 我管你他妈的预言
Press me, and see prophecy ignored.
我正是为了实现预言 就在今日
I but wish to fulfill it, this very day.
预备
Ready.
出发
March.
那就快说 让我们瞧瞧诸神的能耐
Speak then, and let us gauge divinity.
我看见了很有趣的一件事
My eyes fell upon most curious sight,
就是从房间里看见的
witnessed from my cell.
您妻子的奴隶晚上偷偷摸摸地进去
Your wife's slave stealing through the night.
她手里拿的东西我很熟悉
In her hand a thing familiar to me.
恐怕您完全蒙在鼓里…
One I fear you may have no knowledge of...
把水和酒都给我备足了
See the litter well stocked with water and wine.
这么热的天气 我不能在瓦里留斯跟前失态
I would not stand before Varinius parched from this fucking heat.
是 主人
Yes, Domina.
盖尤斯
Gaius.
我以为你和手下都去竞技场了呢
I thought you for the arena with your men.
诸神有没有见过你这样的美人
Have the gods ever beheld such beauty?
承蒙夸奖
You flatter.
退下吧
Leave us.
我们要错过约定的时间了
We will be past the appointed hour.
他们可以等
They will wait.
正如我在等
As I have waited,
等待期盼已久的赐福
for blessings longed for...
那一天当然值得纪念
It will be a glorious day.
可你却不想看到那一天
One you would see never arrive.
- 盖尤斯… - 别他妈的哄我
- Gaius... - Do not fucking attempt lie.
我知道这是什么
I know what I hold.
也知道你要它做什么
And the intent it carries.
为什么
Why?
因为你不配拥有继承人
Because you are not worthy of an heir.
你不配跟我在一起
You are not worthy of me.
我们已经形同陌路了吗
Have we drifted so far?
我们曾经那么相爱
From the love we once held?
那份爱已经远远地离开了海岸
It is a speck upon distant shore.
小得看不见了
Too small to draw notice.
我一定要抱上孩子
I will hold my child in my arms.
你也要扮演好母亲和妻子的角色
And you will play part of dutiful mother and wife.
我不干
I will not.
你要听从丈夫的命令
You will do as your husband commands.
那我希望瓦里留斯用温柔的语气说出来
Then I pray Varinius gives them with softer voice.
瓦里留斯
Varinius?
我父亲为了我的大好前途
My father dissolves our marriage
解除了我们的婚约
in favor of more promising opportunity.
比赛结束后 我就跟他回罗马
I return with him to Rome at the close of the games.
你们竟敢算计我
You conspire against me.
这是逼不得已
We do what we must,
谁叫你越来越让人失望
in face of growing disappointment.
我要去跟你父亲谈谈
I will have words with your father.
有必要吗
To what end?
他当初答应让我们在一起
He allowed you my hand only because I begged
只因我泪汪汪地诉说我有多么爱你
with teary eye, wet with thoughts of love.
但现在我没有眼泪了
They now stand dry.
就像没有雨水滋润的沙漠
A desert deprived of rain.
我们之间什么都没有了吗
Is there nothing left between us?
只有回忆了
Memories only.
不过终究会消失
Yet they too shall fade.
来吧
Come.
让我们最后一次作为夫妻
Let us present ourselves as husband and wife.
观看比赛
For the last time.
民众开始不高兴了
The crowd has turned to sour mood.
这可不能怪他们
We can place no blame.
要怪就怪迟迟不来的某人吧
Except perhaps upon cause of delay.
抱歉
Apologies.
我夫君遇到了意料之外的事情
My husband found himself distracted by unexpected concerns.
那一定是很重要的事情吧
Matters of great import then,
让所有的贵客和卡普亚全体子民等你
to keep honored guest and all of Capua waiting.
确实是很紧急的事情
It was of a pressing nature.
在我看来 过去的事就过去吧
I would condemn such transgressions to distant past,
要着眼于更值得关注的未来
and turn eye toward more deserving future.
我曾经为此夜不能寐
Such thoughts kept sleep at bay.
希望今天的场面能让你高兴起来
I pray the conclusion of this day brings you comfort.
正如你的赐福让民众高兴起来一样
As you have brought to all touched by your divine presence.
那我们别等了 开始吧
Let us begin, and see it come to pass.
还等什么呢
What are we waiting for?
快点开始
Get on with it!
卡普亚的子民们
Citizens of Capua!
我们今日齐聚于此
We gather this day to witness an end
欣赏由鄙人普布利乌斯•瓦里留斯带来的
to the storied games of your humble editor,
传奇之战的谢幕
Publius Varinius.
而在闭幕之时
And in their closing,
我当然要尊重
know that I have not forgone the mores
正午行刑的习俗
of noonday execution.
不过行刑者的身份要提高到骁将的级别
But rather, find tradition exalted to position of the primus!
每一场比赛的胜负
And each contest that leads us to it
直接决定谁有权为罗马主持正义
shall determine which men stand worthy to deliver the justice of Rome!
让我们停止等待 迎接鲜血的盛宴吧
Let spectacles of blood no longer hold pause!
有请撒姆尼角斗士 麦科特
Enter Mycter Samnite!
有请鱼盔角斗士 艾比隆
Enter Abiron Murmillo!
希望诸神让我们度过
May the gods bless us with a day
永垂青史的一天
forever etched upon memory.
开战
Begin!
杀 杀 杀
Kill! Kill! Kill!
真是惊天动地的表演
A display to shake the heavens!
蒙卡图 你真会给角斗士配对呀
You possess a gift for the pairing of gladiators, Mercato!
你有没有想过到罗马去做生意
Have you ever considered plying such trade in Rome?
您抬举我了 民政官
You honor me, Praetor.
可惜我的风水宝地是卡普亚
Yet my fortunes are tied to Capua.
是不是凡有点名气的人 你都想挖走啊
Is it your intent to spirit away everyone of note?
哪里哪里 就几个
I have thoughts toward but a few.
你丈夫的眼神似乎酝酿着狂风暴雨啊
Your husband's eyes betray darkening storm.
他在我的卧房里看到了不该看到的东西
He has made unfortunate discovery, within my bedchambers.
真是不该啊
Unfortunate indeed.
终于到了决定骁将的最后一场比赛
We reach final contest before the primus!
谁能表现出有如神助的实力
Who shall prove himself a god,
拥有为罗马人杀戮叛贼的权利
worthy to take vengeance against the enemies of Rome?
有请重装角斗士 玛索利亚斯
Enter Masonius Hoplomachus!
有请鱼盔角斗士 斯特拉博
Enter Strabo Murmillo!
杀 杀 杀
Kill! Kill! Kill!
精彩的对决
A fine showing.
将永远为狂热的民众所铭记
To be forever remembered by adoring crowd.
正如赐予他们如此盛宴的
As will the name Varinius,
你瓦里留斯的名字
who bestows such generous gifts.
的确 他永远不会被忘记
Indeed. He shall never be forgotten.
有的人就未必了
Same cannot be said of all men.
行刑开始了
The executions begin.
杀 杀 杀
Kill! Kill! Kill!
两个人对付一支军队
Two against an army?
我可不看好你们的胜率
I do not care for your odds.
那你就等着瞧好了
You will see them towards our favor.
你知道怎么做吗
You are clear to your purpose?
我们会办成的
We will see it done.
知道有你在身边
It gives strength.
给了我勇气和力量
Knowing you stand with me.
我们得快点
We must work quickly.
如果你们还信神
If any of you hold faith in any gods,
那就赶紧向他们祈祷
now would be time to fucking entreat them.
快 快
Quick! Quick!
汉尼拔来了
Hannibal stands at our gates!
这是罗马人用来吓唬小孩的说法
A phrase used to invoke fear among the children of Rome.
迦太基野兽的幽灵…
A specter of the Carthaginian animal...
多少年了 我一直想重回竞技场
For many years I have dreamed of my return to the arena.
我很荣幸
It is an honor.
能与你并肩上场
To stand beside you upon the sands.
汉尼拔最终命丧罗马人剑下
Hannibal passed from this life at the end of a Roman sword!
你们的时辰到了
Your time has come.
叛贼斯巴达克斯终有一天也是同样的下场
A fate that will one day be shared by the rebel Spartacus!
我们的剑没有开锋
They give us swords absent fucking edge.
也没有胜利的希望
Absent hope of victory as well.
那就让他们知道 给我们剑是大错特错
Let us prove them fools for giving us swords at all.
杀了这帮畜生
Kill those Bastards!
准备受死吧 你们这些混蛋
I hope you die! Fuckers!
我要你们开膛破肚 臭囚犯
I wanna see your insides, prisoners!
今天真是荣幸啊
This day grants undeserved honor.
我一直希望跟最伟大的冠军
I have longed to share the sands with Gannicus,
甘尼克斯同场竞技
the greatest champion ever to enter the arena.
这儿没什么冠军
There stand no champions here.
只有凡人和他们的命运
Only men and their fates.
谁能领导罗马的行刑者
Yet who shall lead the forces of Rome?
谁配得上如此传奇的一战
Who deserves such storied mantle?
你是巴蒂塔斯家的人
You are from the House of Batiatus?
只有一个人
There stands but one!
上辈子的事儿
A lifetime ago.
现在你要上场
And now you take to the sands,
要你兄弟们的命
to claim the lives of your brothers?
既然他们必须死 我就送他们体面地上路
If they must fall, I would see them to honorable death.
真正的竞技场之神
A true God of the Arena!
至少杀他们的人 心里还记挂着他们
Given by one who yet holds them to heart.
有请甘尼克斯
I give you Gannicus!
甘尼克斯
Gannicus!
甘尼克斯 甘尼克斯
Gannicus! Gannicus! Gannicus!
我都要怀疑这鬼计划靠不靠谱了
I begin to question fucking plan.
我们各有任务
We are committed.
要有信心 准备好…
Steel nerve, and be ready for
她是我妻子
She was my wife.
而你是我兄弟
And you my brother.
不
No!
他是我的
He is mine!
就是这里
This is the place.
你们干什么
You there?!
站住
Halt!
高卢人终于要死了
The Gaul finally nears his end.
早就该这样了
A fate long overdue.
他们耽搁太久了
They take too long.
我们必须等待 不然努力就白费了
We must wait or see effort failed.
我也不希望对她动感情
I never wanted to feel what I felt for her!
我不想这样的
I never wanted any of this!
莱斯克斯
Rhaskos!
操
Fuck.
稳住
Wait.
烧得不够快
It's not working fast enough!
链子
The chains.
缠住柱子
Wrap them around the supports.
拉
Pull!
我送你去见她 兄弟
I will send you to her arms, brother.
拉
Pull!
冲
Now!
出什么事了
What's happening?!
快离开
Let's get out of here.
清开道路
Clear way!
快清开道路
Clear fucking way
蒙卡图
Mercato!
我要救你们出去 兄弟
I would see us gone from here, brother.
杀掉他们
Kill them!
来帮忙
Give hand!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
科萨特斯
Cossutius!
可以出去了
The path is clear!
斯巴达克斯又一次耍了你
Spartacus once again makes fool of you.
你在元老院的好日子结束了
Your days in the Senate have found their end!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
我们该走了
We must move!
不行 我们要找到奥诺玛默斯
No, we must find Oenomaus!
这边
This way.
盖尤斯
Gaius...
救我
Help me Please...
救我 求你了
Help me, please.
我没有你和你女儿想的那么傻
I'm not the fool you and your daughter think me.
帮我扶他
Help me with him.
走 我能跟上
Go. I will follow.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
我已经受够了角斗比赛
I have had my fill of games.
我们永远离开竞技场吧
Let us leave this arena forever.
市民们
Citizens!
市民们 保持冷静
Citizens, calm yourselves!
快召集你的手下
Gather your fucking men!
来 我负责送你们回宅子
Come. I would see you safe to the villa.
盖尤斯
Gaius...
我父亲呢
Where is my father?
他死了 死于斯巴达克斯之手
He has fallen, at the hands of Spartacus.
可我们活下来了
We will survive this.
我们俩
Together.
还是恩爱夫妻嘛
As husband and wife.